Almeda C. Vickery Papers
Almeda C. Vickery Papers
1908-1962
Vickery, Almeda Campbell.
2 linear ft.
Daughter of Kate Campbell Vickery and Charles Rowe Vickery, American Congregationalist missionaries to India and Singapore. Includes photographs, writings, notes, and diaries, as well as Vickery family genealogical material.
3174719
Biographical History
Almeda Campbell Vickery (1907-) was the daughter of Kate Campbell Vickery and Charles Rowe Vickery, American missionaries to India and Singapore.
Kate Campbell Vickery (dates unknown) was an American missionary, author, and lecturer. She traveled to India with her husband Charles and daughter Almeda in 1908, and spent the next three years there and in Singapore, eventually returning to the United States in 1911. In the United States, she continued her missionary work by sharing her experiences with the public as a lecturer, making appearances across the northeastern states, particularly New York and Connecticut. Dressed in Indian clothing, she would discuss the needs of orphans and widows in India while also telling of her own work and experiences. She was also the author of at least one article and two books on India and mission work.
Charles Rowe Vickery (1873-1943) was an American Congregationalist minister and missionary. Born in Lansing, Michigan, he graduated from Syracuse University in 1900, and then from Drew Theological Seminary in 1903. He was ordained a minister in 1905, also marrying Kate Campbell the same year. After their daughter Almeda was born in 1907, they soon departed for India in 1908, eventually returning in 1911. Upon the United States becoming involved in World War I, he went to London as war secretary for the YMCA, overseeing their warehouses which supplied U.S. troops in Europe. Returning after the war to the United States, the family moved to Hartford and then to New Haven, Connecticut, where Charles died in 1943.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Almeda C. Vickery Papers includes biographical material, correspondence, memorabilia, and writings.
Biographical material is comprised of photocopied notes on Vickery family genealogy, starting with Charles and Kate and tracing back to the Mayflower.
Correspondence is comprised of one later postcard to Kate, a series of letters from the Library of Congress Copyright Office regarding Kate's published work, and three letters about missionary work written from India.
Memorabilia is comprised of Charles' diary while stationed in England as the head of a YMCA warehouse in World War I; photographs and negatives from India and Singapore; printed material, including clippings related to India; and promotional material related to Kate's work as a writer and lecturer about missions in India.
Writings is comprised of manuscripts and typescripts of articles about India, written by Kate, as well as Kate's lecture notes about mission work.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into four series and arranged alphabetically by title and type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Vickery, Almeda Campbell.; Vickery, Charles Rowe.; Vickery, Kate Campbell.; Ramabai Sarasvati, 1858-1922.; Clergy -- United States.; Missionaries.; Genealogy.; India -- Missions.; South Asia -- Missions.; Singapore -- Missions.; Congregationalism -- Missions.; Congregational churches -- Clergy.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photograph albums.; Lecture notes.; Negatives (photographs); Typescripts.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Diaries.; Clergy.; Missionaries.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Bulk of collection, gift of Almeda C. Vickery, 1965.
Genealogical material, gift of Alfred T. Colette, 1967.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Vickery genealogy, 1908-1962; 3 folders; photocopied notes (Box 1)
    Gift of Alfred T. Colette, 1967
- Correspondence
  - Hersey, Grace, 1962; single postcard (Box 1)
  - Library of Congress Copyright Office, 1946-1955 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1910; three letters written from Singapore and India, related to missionary work (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Diary and scrapbook, 1918; Charles R. Vickery's diary while in charge of YMCA warehouse in London (Box 1)
  - Negatives, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Photograph album, 1908-1910; scenes of the family in India and Singapore (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1908-1962 (Box 2)
  - Postcard, 1908-1962; image of Parbati Hill & Temple, Poona, with handwritten description on reverse (Box 2)
  - Printed material, 1922-1929; includes material related to Indian social reformer Ramabai Sarasvati, a subject of Kate Vickery's writings (Box 2)
  - Promotional material, 1908-1962; two fliers promoting Kate Campbell Vickery's lectures and books on missionary work (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Behind Bungalo, 1908-1962 (Box 2)
  - Eldest son's wife, 1908-1962 (Box 2)
  - [Lecture notes], 1929-1945; 4 folders; notebooks, notepads, and loose notes of lecture outlines (Box 2)
  - Mama's Sloat busy day, 1908-1962; typescript of short play (Box 2)
  - Mihr-Un-Nissa, queen of women, 1908-1962 (Box 2)
  - The Missionary Review of the World, vol. XLV, no. 9 (Sept., 1922), includes article "Ramabai, The Hindu Widows' Friend," by Kate Campbell Vickery (Box 2)
  - The most unforgettable character I've met, 1908-1962; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - My other Shantabai, 1908-1962 (Box 2)
  - Pandita Ramabai, 1908-1962; 3 folders; one manuscript and two typescripts, possibly representing two separate texts with the same title (Box 2)
  - The Rajahs of India, 1908-1962 (Box 2)
  - Shantabai, 1908-1962 (Box 2)
  - With our evangelistic missionary in Baroda, 1908-1962; manuscript and typescript; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - [Untitled play], 1908-1962; typescript (Box 2)